we're talking about tissue
hypothyroidism now this is a concept
under the basis of cellular
hypothyroidism and or the lack of
getting tissue adequate levels of the
thyroid hormone in the tissues
themselves from a conventional
standpoint when we treat the thyroid
what we do is we treat with an exogenous
replacement hormone and we look for the
negative feedback response as the TSH
will get suppressed on paper this works
because on paper the goal is simply to
give exogenous hormone pretty much
usually T4 and you just want to watch
the T4 levels go up and you won't watch
the TSH go down now the problem with
treating like this is you're treating
directly based on paper this is a paper
treatment this is a numerical treatment
this does not take into account the
patient's symptomatic response if I were
to treat or direct a a response a
therapeutic response based on the TSH
being suppressed that would be no
different than if I were to treat
someone low te and put them on te and
only look at the LH levels being
suppressed without actually looking at
the testosterone level or without
looking at the symptomatic Improvement
in the patient that's a flaw approach
but that is the approach that we've
typically been taught unfortunately
treating based on the suppression of
Tropic hormones has become the
convention and the guideline gold
standard and here's where the concept of
tissue hypothyroidism comes into play
tissue hypothyroidism otherwise some
people refer to as um Cellar
hypothyroidism is essentially the
treatment refractory point you you treat
the patient with the exogenous hormone
their levels look great on paper the
serum levels go up the free levels go up
yeah they should be great right should
have symptomatic Improvement right
because the numbers look great but the
problem is you're not getting any kind
of symptomatic resolution and that's
because a lot of the hormones benefits
are exerted at the tissue level and this
can apply to both free tea and or free
T4 some of this tissue resistance can be
be can be secondary to chronic disease
chronic dieting chronic physical
emotional stress diabetes insulin
resistance the literature has shown us
that if you have conditions like that
heck even like chronic pain like
fibromyalgia those conditions can reduce
serum levels upwards of 30ish per and
it's speculated it can actually reduce
tissue levels somewhere in the ballpark
of about 70ish % long story short what
we've learned over the last couple of
decades which Dr Grant's been wonderful
at talking about uh things such as the
intracrinology of these hormones now
he's talked ad nauseum about estrad as
as an intracrine hormone we know that
DHT also expresses the vast majority of
his actions also as an intracrine
hormone also they have some paracrine
activity we know that igf-1 also has
some intracrine paracrine activity but
we also now know know that T3 T4 the
thyroid hormones also Express the vast
majority of their activity as an
intracrine hormone and again a lot of
the the benefits of the hormones come at
the tissue level so ultimately the goal
is to treat the patient symptomatically
and not really chase the numbers